Leah: Coding reviews are an integral part of the
software development process, but there are several
different ‘review methods’ that can used and
each has its own specific benefits and downsides
depending on your project and team structure.
Let’s look at some of the most common
methods for conducting coding reviews.
Chris: Instant code review—also known
as pair programming title on screen
In this type of review, there are two developers, one
will be on the keyboard producing the code and the other
reviewing it as it is being written, paying attention to
potential issues and giving ideas for code improvement on
the go as well as identifying potential future problems.
Leah: The developer typing is identified as the driver
and the developer reviewing the code is the navigator.
When using this method, the two
programmers will switch roles frequently.
By working together through the process of finding a
solution you increase the opportunity to get it right.
The ‘driver’ is able to focus all their attention on
the task of coding knowing that the ‘navigator’ is there
to observe, give guidance and support when required.
Chris: This type of review is useful when aiming for
fast high-quality code and a reduced cost of development.
It is also useful for personal development, as the pair
can learn from each other and can help to improve morale.
But there are also downsides to this type of review
as the pair need to work effectively together
as a team, and personal egos may impact on this
by one or other of the team feeling intimidated.
You may also have the junior developer ‘driving’
and the more experienced developer ‘navigating’
who may get frustrated that the driver is
too slow ultimately resulting in conflict.
Leah: Inspection
Chris: title on screen
Leah: This type of review is typically carried
out by peers, who are trained to review code by
looking at errors using well defined processes.
It is commonly referred to as a Fagan inspection
after the inventor of the process, ‘Michael Fagan’.
Chris: The principle behind this is that the
requirements are agreed at the beginning.
For each activity or operation, an
entry and exit criteria are specified.
The reviewer can then compare the results of the
activity to the pre-defined exit criteria, to
validate that it has complied with these criteria.
The steps followed in the inspection are.
Bold titles on screen
Overview- the assignment of roles and the exit
requirements for each activity are established.
Preparation- all those involved in the review prepare for
their roles, familiarise themselves with the requirements
for each section, inspect any supporting materials and
note down any questions or concerns that they may have.
Inspection- this is when the actual review
takes place, and any errors are identified.
Rework- developers correct any errors
that were found during the inspection.
Follow up- a moderator checks over the rework to ensure
that all the identified errors have been corrected
and no new ones have been created during the fix.
Walkthrough title on screen
Is a form of software peer review where the lead
designer or coder walks the members of the development
team and other stakeholders through the product.
Those involved can ask questions or comment
on errors or other concerns they may have.
This type of review is useful in that it gives
a broad overview of the product but is not as in
depth as other review types and lacks the direct
focus of on training and process development.
Technical review title on screen
This type of review is carried out by a team of
qualified developers who will undertake a peer review
of the product and look at it in detail, to ensure
that the product meets the suitability criteria for
its intended use, and any variance from the original
design and specification requirements that were agreed.
The review team may also make
recommendations for alternative solutions.
Technical reviews differ from inspections in their ability
to suggest direct alterations to the product reviewed,
rather than any focus on training or process improvement.